Guide to the Workmen's Circle/Der Arbeter Ring Branch 304 Records
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
Workmen's Circle/Der Arbeter Ring Branch 304 records
1909-1971
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections Box 352900 Seattle, WA 98195-2900
1859
1859-001
Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring.$bBranch No. 304 (Seattle, Wash.)
10 cubic feet 15 boxes, plus one oversize folder
Records of a mutual benefit society and cultural-social organization for members of the Jewish working class
In April of 1892, a group of Jewish garment workers from New York City's Lower East Side formed a mutual aid society called the Workingmen’s Circle. This small collective soon grew to a membership of 300, and it officially became known as the Workmen’s Circle (Der Arbeter Ring in Yiddish) in 1900. The Workmen’s Circle provided benefits that poor immigrants were otherwise denied: life insurance, health benefits, unemployment relief, homes for the aged, and funeral assistance. By 1920 there were over 80,000 members, and The Workmen’s Circle had become one of the largest Jewish organizations in America.
The programs initiated by the Workmen's Circle encompassed a host of social, cultural, and political issues deemed important to the Jewish community. In addition to promoting labor rights and the strengthening of trade unions, the organization provided educational and cultural programs that emphasized Jewish heritage through theater, music, literature, summer camps, and Yiddish instruction. The Workmen's Circle also sold war bonds to provide support during both World Wars, and partnered with other Jewish organizations to actively promote and fund the settlement and expansion of Israel during the early years of its existence. After World War II, the organization de-emphasized their socialist leanings in an effort to distance themselves from communist affiliation.
The Seattle, Washington branch of the Workmen's Circle -- Branch 304 -- was organized in 1909, and their first location was a rented store on 14th Avenue and Main Street. In 1920, the members bought a building at 120 21st Avenue that had previously been a blacksmith shop. Property was then purchased for the organization at 1614 East Union Street in 1937, with the grand opening of this location taking place in December 1942. Activities in Seattle included summer picnics, festive observances of Jewish holidays, New Years Eve celebrations, banquets, and lectures. Though Branch 304 eventually closed its doors in 1973, the Workmen's Circle organization continues to operate in several cities across the country.
The Workmen's Circle Records collection consists of papers gathered by the Seattle branches of the organization during their sixty-year lifespan. Materials include: biographical and historical data and correspondence (1925-1971), financial records (1909-1969), tax records (1943-1961), minutes (1941-1968), membership lists (1909-1960), and handbills (1932), among other items.
Donated by Ben Stein, 1972-1973. One folder containing five handbills advertising the 23rd annual Picnic and Dance donated by Bill Clifford on July 27, 2007.
This collection forms part of Washington State Jewish Archives.
Open to all users.
Workmen's Circle/Der Arbeter Ring Branch 304 photograph collection (PH0769)
Ben Stein papers (1916)
Stein, Ben,$dapproximately 1890-; Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring.$bBranch No. 304 (Seattle, Wash.)$vArchives; Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.); Federated Jewish Fund & Council of Greater Seattle; Washington State Jewish Archives (University of Washington)
Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Jewish Americans; Labor History; Labor Unions; Diaries
- Seattle Branches, Series 1
  Materials related to branches 304 (men) and 304B (women) of the Workmen's Circle organization in Seattle, Washington.
  - Charters of Workmen's Circle Branches 304 and 304B, 1909, 1929
  - Biographical and Historical Data, undated (Box-folder 1/1-3)
  - Biographical and Historical Data of Workmen's Circle Branch 304B (Women's Club), undated (Box-folder 1/4)
  - By Laws, undated (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Incoming Letters
    - American Financial and Development Corporation for Israel, 1953 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - American Red Magen David for Israel, 1961
    - American Organization for Rehabilitation Through Training Federation, 1954
    - Amon, Sol (Mrs.), 1954
    - Anderson Water Tours, 1934-1937
    - Aronson, H., 1956
    - Aschert Bros., 1951
    - Benezia, Jack L., 1953
    - Bergman, Fred H., undated
    - Bernstein, Martin, 1953
    - Blatt, J., 1953
    - Bronx I. L. Peretz School, undated
    - Bronx Workmen's Circle School No. 15, undated
    - B'nai B'rith Lodge 503, 1948-1953
    - Caplin, Louis, 1953
    - Caroline Kline Galland Home, 1964
    - Caroline Kline Galland Home Building Fund, 1963-1971
    - China, Republic of - Consulate, 1937
    - Citizens Federal Savings, 1963
    - City of Hope, 1955-1957
    - Cleveland Workmen's Circle Chorus and Mandolin Ensemble, 1954
    - Cohan, A. and Co., 1936
    - Cohan, Helen K., 1956
    - Cohan's Camera Center, 1971
    - Cohn, Merle D., 1948
    - Credit Union National Association, 1933
    - Credit Union National Extension Bureau, 1925
    - Development Corporation for Israel, 1964
    - Diamond, Izze, 1952
    - Diamond. Josef, 1965
    - Dimarco Reception Committee, 1954
    - Docter, Harry, undated
    - Docter, Raymond H., 1956
    - Dore, John F., 1933
    - Durabuilt Luggage Mfg. Co., Inc., 1935
    - Eisenhower, Dwight D., 1954
      Form letter
    - Federated Jewish Fund and Council, 1953-1959
    - Franco and Bensussen, 1957
    - Fraternal Center of Brooklyn, undated
    - Free Voice of Labor, undated
    - Friends of Israel Histadrut, Seattle Chapter, 1957-1960
    - Gediman, Arthur M., 1953
    - Gierowitz, Nathan, 1957
    - Glazer, Mary, 1963
    - Goldfarb, Samuel E., 1953-1956
    - Goldstein, Stanley, undated
    - Gordan, S. A., 1954-1957
    - Group Health Cooperative of Puget Sound, 1953
    - Gulbranson, J. R., 1953
    - Gustanoff, Abe L., 1953
    - Habunim, 1957 (Box-folder 1/7)
    - Hall, Hazel C., 1951
    - Hanehin, Harry, 1962
    - Health Insurance Institution - Kupet - Holim, 1965
    - Hosiery Workers, American Federation of, 1954
    - Israel, Consulate of, 1952
    - Israel Histadrut Campaign, 1963-1964
    - Israelite Press L. T. D., 1956
    - Jacobs, Jerome B., 1952
    - Jacqueline F. Rubenstein Memorial Committee, 1968
    - Jewish Club of Washington, 1957
    - Jewish Community Center, Seattle, 1965
    - Jewish Community Centers Building Fund Campaign, 1965
    - Jewish Consumptive Relief Society, Seattle Ladies Auxiliary, 1956
    - Jewish Chronic Disease Hospital, 1956
    - Jewish Institute for the Blind, 1962
    - Jewish Labor Committee, 1943-1958
    - Jewish National Home for Asthmatic Children, 1954-1956
    - Jewish Welfare Board, National, 1952, 1957
    - Jewish Yearbook of the Northwest, undated
    - Jews. Congregation Temple de Hirsch, 1955-1960
    - Jews. Herzal Jewish Culture Foundation, 1956
    - Kaminoff, Ida, 1956 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - Kelly, Marguerite, 1957
    - Kennedy, John F., 1961-1963
      Form letters
    - Klein, Isadore, 1956
    - Klein, Sarah, 1956
    - Kossen, Carl K., 1960-1961
    - Kossen, Jack, 1954-1955
    - Kraft, Rose, 1961
    - Kraus and Sons, 1938
    - Lane, W. D., 1925
    - Leather Workers International Union of America, AFL-CIO, 1924
    - Leavitt, Ida, undated
    - Leavitt, Sydney, 1963
    - Lemchen, Phillip (Mrs.), undated
    - Levison, Bernard, 1956
    - Lindsay, Margaret, 1954
    - Lycette, Diamond and Sylvester, 1952-1964
    - Malatoff, M. J., 1951
    - Martin, 1953
    - Maslan and Maslan, 1947-1950
    - Maslan, Maslan and Hanan, 1954-1963
    - Mezistrano, Joe, 1953
    - Miller, H., 1958
    - Miller, Sam, 1957
    - Mosler, George R., 1960
    - National Committee for Labor Israel, 1957
    - National Committee for Labor Israel Histadrut, 1963
    - National Council of Jewish Women, 1957
    - National Jewish Hospital of Denver, 1954, 1959
    - Newell, A. B. and Son, 1927-1931
    - Northern Pacific Railway Co., 1964
    - Pacific First Federal Savings, 1963
    - Peoples National Bank of Washington, 1952
    - Premier Artists Representatives, 1951
    - Press, Lou, 1959
    - Prottas and Levitt, 1954
    - Puget Sound Mutual Savings Bank, 1963
    - Raine, Jacob, 1952-1957
    - Radinsky, Jack, 1962
    - Ross, Morris, 1962
    - Rubin, Sam and Clara, undated
    - Russell Sage Foundation, Division of Remedial Loans, 1925
    - Saltman, Leah, undated (Box-folder 1/9)
    - Semon, Stuart, 1956
    - Seattle Fire Department, 1946
    - Seattle Lighting Department, 1939
    - Seattle Public Schools, 1959-1961
    - Seattle Hebrew School, 1953, 1965
    - Seattle - King County Department of Public Health, 1951
    - Seattle Labor College, 1927
    - Seattle Zionist Council, 1952-1956
    - Sherr, Harry, 1929
    - Shulman, Abe, 1945
    - Shulman, L. Michael, 1944-1945
    - Silverman, Libby, 1968
    - Stern, Will, 1957-1959
    - Stutzker, A., 1943
    - Sterling, Bernard, 1951
    - Sunnyshore Acres, 1951
    - Trade Union Institute, 1941
    - Turner, Ida, 1964
    - Tussman, Louis, 1957
    - Twersky, Meyer (Mrs.), 1953
    - United EIAS Service, 1955
    - United Jewish Appeal, 1953-1957
    - United States - Information Agency, 1962
    - United States - Labor Department, 1961
    - United States - State Department, 1935
    - United States - Treasury Department, 1932-1944
    - Vziel, Leon E., 1961-1963
    - Victor, 1953-1957
    - Volstein, L., 1939
    - Wagner, Joseph H., 1955
    - Washington - Licenses Department, 1960
    - Washington - Liquor Control Board, 1934
    - Washington Division of Savings and Loan Associations, 1954-1958
    - Washington Mutual Savings Bank, 1963
    - Weintraub, Meyer, undated
    - Wendrow, N., 1953
    - West, George R., 1955
    - Who's Who in Jewish Labor, undated
    - Weiner, Morris, 1943
    - Workmen's Circle Branch 305E, 1953
    - Workmen's Circle Branch 578, 685, 1949, 1964
    - Workmen's Circle Home for the Aged (N. Y. Branches, Inc.), 1956
    - Workmen's Circle School #5, 1954
    - Workmen's Circle National Campaign for Cancer Hospital at City of Hope, 1950-1951
    - Workmen's Circle Sanitarium, 1939
    - Yaffee, Jack, 1953-1956
    - Young Circle League, undated
    - Unidentified, 1956
    - Hebrew Sheltering and Immigration Aid Society, 1926, undated (Box-folder 1/10)
    - Jewish Family and Child Service, 1950-1954 (Box-folder 1/11)
    - Mitchell, Hugh B., 1946 (Box-folder 1/12)
    - Ringold, Solie, 1961-1965 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Incoming Letters - Workmen's Circle National Office, 1930-1971 (Box-folder 2/1-3)
  - Incoming Letters - 304B, 304B was the women's organization
    - Chanin, N., 1945 (Box-folder 2/4)
    - Cooper, Dora, 1961
    - Federated Jewish Fund and Council, 1957
    - Workmen's Circle National Office, 1955-1959
  - Incoming Letters - 304Y, 304Y was the youth organization
    - Baskin, Joseph, 1942 (Box-folder 2/5)
    - Knox, Israel, 1942
  - Outgoing Letters, 1925-1970 (Box-folder 2/6-10)
  - Outgoing Letters - 304B, 1931-1961 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - Yiddish Correspondence, 1927-1969 (Box-folder 3)
  - Tax Records, 1943-1961 (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Legal Documents, 1914-1966 (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Insurance Policies, 1939-1961 (Box-folder 4/3)
  - Financial Records, 1920-1971 (Box-folder 4/4-6)
  - Financial Records - 304B, 1938 (Box-folder 4/7)
  - Financial Records - Membership Ledgers, 1909-1960 (Box-folder 5-6)
  - Financial Records - Cash books, 1909-1960 (Box-folder 6)
  - Financial Records - Receipt Books, 1942-1971 (Box-folder 7-8)
  - Financial Records - Cash Books, 1951-1969 (Box-folder 8)
  - Minutes Book, 1956-1957 (Box-folder 9/1)
  - Minutes, 1941-1968 (Box-folder 9/2)
  - Minutes - 304B, 1937-1946 (Box-folder 9/3)
    in Yiddish
  - Reports, 1940-1962 (Box-folder 9/4-5)
  - Resolutions, 1929, 1942, 1952, 1963 (Box-folder 9/6)
  - News Releases, 1949-1962 (Box-folder 9/7)
  - Writings, 1954-1962, undated (Box-folder 9/8)
  - Writings - Invitations, 1943-1959 (Box-folder 9/9)
  - Writings - Yiddish, 1957-1965, undated (Box-folder 9/10-11)
  - Membership Campaign Materials, 1951-1956 (Box-folder 10/1)
  - Election Ballots, 1938-1948 (Box-folder 10/2)
  - Bulletins, 1925-1967 (Box-folder 10/3-4)
  - Newsletters and Bulletins - Other Branches and National, 1929-1965 (Box-folder 10/5-19)
  - Ephemera - Promotional, 1926-1962 (Box-folder 11/1-2)
  - Ephemera - Other Branches and National, 1925-1961 (Box-folder 11/3-4)
  - Ephemera - Yiddish, undated (Box-folder 11/5-6)
  - Ephemera - Jewish, Non-Workmen's Circle, Seattle, 1929-1965 (Box-folder 11/7-9)
  - Ephemera - Jewish, Non-Workmen's Circle, Non-Seattle, 1917-1966 (Box-folder 11/10-11)
  - Ephemera - Jewish, Non-Workmen's Circle, Non-Seattle, 1917-1966 (Box-folder 12/1-7)
  - Ephemera - Socialist and Labor-Related, 1927-1954 (Box-folder 12/8-9)
  - Programs, 1927-1960 (Box-folder 12/10-13)
  - Programs, 1927-1960 (Box-folder 13/1)
  - Souvenir Programs, 1927-1949 (Box-folder 13/2)
  - Programs - Other Branches and National, 1933 (Box-folder 13/3)
  - Souvenir - Other Branches and National, 1925-1962 (Box-folder 13/4-7)
  - Lists, 1909-1964 (Box-folder 13/8-10)
  - Notes, 1934-1967 (Box-folder 13/11)
  - Notes (Yiddish), undated (Box-folder 14/1)
  - Meeting Notices, 1931-1953 (Box-folder 14/2)
  - Meeting Notices - Lectures, 1927-1931 (Box-folder 14/3)
  - Clippings, 1933-1956, 1968 (Box-folder 14/4-5)
  - Photographs, 1931-1935, undated; Placeholder only; materials relocated to PH Coll 769 (Box-folder 14/6)
  - Awards and Certificates, 1922-1947 (Box-folder 14/7)
  - Memorabilia, 1931-1952 (Box-folder 14/8-9)
  - Blank Forms, undated (Box-folder 14/10)
  - Insurance - Other Branches and National, 1913-1959 (Box-folder 14/11)
  - Educational Materials - Other Branches and National, undated (Box-folder 14/12)
  - Miscellaneous Re: Genocide Legislation and Immigration Policy, undated (Box-folder 14/13)
  - Youth Camp, undated (Box-folder 15/1)
- Union Street Building, Series 2
  Materials related to the purchase and renovation of the Workmen's Circle property at 1614 East Union Street in Seattle, Washington.
  - Specifications, 1937-1939 (Box-folder 15/2)
  - Minutes, 1937-1941 (Box-folder 15/3)
  - General Correspondence, 1938-1943 (Box-folder 15/4)
  - Agendas, 1942 (Box-folder 15/5)
  - Financial Records, 1938-1942 (Box-folder 15/6)
  - Contracts, 1938-1939 (Box-folder 15/7)
  - Resolutions, 1940 (Box-folder 15/8)
  - Notes, 1941, undated (Box-folder 15/9)
- Northwestern District Committee, Series 3
  Materials related to a regional decision-making arm of the Workmen's Circle organization, established July 27, 1924 in Seattle, Washington.
  - General Correspondence, 1934-1958 (Box-folder 15/10-13)
  - Minutes, 1940-1941 (Box-folder 15/14)
  - Financial Records, 1957-1961 (Box-folder 15/15)
  - Lists, 1932, undated (Box-folder 15/16)
  - Clippings, undated (Box-folder 15/17)
  - Memorabilia, 1921-1953 (Box-folder 15/18)
  - Photographs (Box-folder 15/19)
    Placeholder only; materials relocated to PH Coll 769
  - Ephemera, 1932-1950 (Box-folder 15/20)
    Includes 5 handbills advertising the 23rd annual Picnic and Dance